<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wpcontractors.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wpcontractors.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-17T18:47:27+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wpcontractors.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">WP Contractors</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why we started {{ site.title }}</title><link href="https://www.wpcontractors.com/blog/2020/04/01/why-we-started/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why we started {{ site.title }}" /><published>2020-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wpcontractors.com/blog/2020/04/01/why-we-started</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wpcontractors.com/blog/2020/04/01/why-we-started/">&lt;article class=&quot;node node-blog clearfix&quot; about=&quot;/content/why-we-started-wp-contractors&quot;
  typeof=&quot;sioc:Post sioct:BlogPost&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span property=&quot;dc:title&quot; content=&quot;Why we started WP Contractors&quot; class=&quot;rdf-meta element-hidden&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span
    property=&quot;sioc:num_replies&quot; content=&quot;0&quot; datatype=&quot;xsd:integer&quot; class=&quot;rdf-meta element-hidden&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-body field-type-text-with-summary field-label-hidden container&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The driver behind launching this platform is simple. Our success with Drupal Contractors founded in
            2011 &lt;a href=&quot;https://drupalcontractors.com&quot;&gt;https://drupalcontractors.com&lt;/a&gt;, now at 300+ Drupal
            resources, has shown us that our approach in cultivating one-to-one relationships with engineers,
            architects, project managers and testing resources is working. In 2017 I partnered with long-time
            Drupal contributor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drupal.org/u/albert-volkman&quot;&gt;Albert Volkman&lt;/a&gt; as our CTO
            asking he focus on ensuring and increasing the quality of our workforce. Being engineers ourselves we
            felt it important to focus on learning what skills individuals have and what projects they are looking
            to connect with on what terms. While simultaneously building relationships with agencies and employers
            and learning as intimantly as we can their needs we are reducing time to hire, increasing retention
            and project success rate for our clients and connecting our workforce with interesting opportunities.
            In 2019 we formed &lt;a href=&quot;http://esteemed.io&quot;&gt;Esteemed.io&lt;/a&gt; to be able to launch additional
            (product or category + contractors.com) properties our first being wpcontractors.com where we hope to
            leverage the experience we have gained in the Drupal community.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;h2&gt;WordPress is a Community&lt;/h2&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Since early on in the history of the world wide web there have always been job and freelancer sites.
            As an early Internet entrepreneur I aso operated a niche site in partnership with Career Builder from
            1996 to 2006 that focused on the changing manufacturing world. I learned there the special
            relationships that people who focus on a particluar niche market are able to form via bonding over the
            specifics of the landscape. How targeted industry content not only helps inform people of goings on,
            or a new direction in their specific niche can not only help them advance and grow in their career and
            finding the next opportunity, not just help find the next ideal team member, but also build a
            community. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;WordPress as many here know is already that. It is why I chose to focus on it as my own career and
            leverage the power of Open Source, and contribute back to it in every way that I could. We view WP
            Contractors as just an extension of the WordPress.org community and a compliment to our sister
            property Drupal Contractors &lt;a
              href=&quot;https://app.drupalcontractors.com&quot;&gt;https://app.drupalcontractors.com&lt;/a&gt;. We work closely with
            the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/about/&quot;&gt;WordPress Association&lt;/a&gt; to find opportunities to sponsor
            and support ongong projects to advance the product. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;In short, we hope you find our platform useful and relevant to our industry of WordPress WCMS
            development. If you have any suggestions please don't hesitate to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:service@esteemed.io&quot;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt;
            so we can improve our offering with the valuable input from our community. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;</content><author><name>Chris McGrath</name></author><category term="wordpress" /><summary type="html">The driver behind launching this platform is simple. Our success with Drupal Contractors founded in 2011 https://drupalcontractors.com, now at 300+ Drupal resources, has shown us that our approach in cultivating one-to-one relationships with engineers, architects, project managers and testing resources is working. In 2017 I partnered with long-time Drupal contributor Albert Volkman as our CTO asking he focus on ensuring and increasing the quality of our workforce. Being engineers ourselves we felt it important to focus on learning what skills individuals have and what projects they are looking to connect with on what terms. While simultaneously building relationships with agencies and employers and learning as intimantly as we can their needs we are reducing time to hire, increasing retention and project success rate for our clients and connecting our workforce with interesting opportunities. In 2019 we formed Esteemed.io to be able to launch additional (product or category + contractors.com) properties our first being wpcontractors.com where we hope to leverage the experience we have gained in the Drupal community. WordPress is a Community Since early on in the history of the world wide web there have always been job and freelancer sites. As an early Internet entrepreneur I aso operated a niche site in partnership with Career Builder from 1996 to 2006 that focused on the changing manufacturing world. I learned there the special relationships that people who focus on a particluar niche market are able to form via bonding over the specifics of the landscape. How targeted industry content not only helps inform people of goings on, or a new direction in their specific niche can not only help them advance and grow in their career and finding the next opportunity, not just help find the next ideal team member, but also build a community. WordPress as many here know is already that. It is why I chose to focus on it as my own career and leverage the power of Open Source, and contribute back to it in every way that I could. We view WP Contractors as just an extension of the WordPress.org community and a compliment to our sister property Drupal Contractors https://app.drupalcontractors.com. We work closely with the WordPress Association to find opportunities to sponsor and support ongong projects to advance the product. In short, we hope you find our platform useful and relevant to our industry of WordPress WCMS development. If you have any suggestions please don't hesitate to reach out so we can improve our offering with the valuable input from our community.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wpcontractors.com/assets/img/wp-contractors-group-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wpcontractors.com/assets/img/wp-contractors-group-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>